<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Papers on Francisco Olivos</title>
    <link>/tags/papers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Papers on Francisco Olivos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Meritocratic Narratives as Cultural Orientations</title>
      <link>/project/children/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The meritocratic principle (Young 1958), which emphasizes the central role of ability and effort for status attainment is losing effectiveness as a collective myth (Lamont 2019). Sociologists argue that meritocratic beliefs, or the narratives that abilities and hard work lead to success, are unfulfilled promises (e.g. Mijs 2016a), as success is not ensured for everyone and societies vary in the strength of the link between education and success in life. The idea that these subjective propositions about the distribution of rewards are legitimations of action and structural conditions for certain groups is becoming common among social scientists (Khan 2011; Mijs 2016a, 2019). Furthermore, the degree to which meritocratic beliefs are accepted and perceived as valid principles of distribution differs between social groups. Privileged families may prefer the meritocratic principle to a larger extent and encourage learning activities (Lareau 2011). According to the findings of Becker and Hadjar (2013), lower social classes (e.g. working classes, lower middle class) are more likely to perceive that success still depends on social origin, social position and family than the upper service class. Specifically, parents affected by negative status-inconsistency, i.e. who have acquired a status below that they would most likely have achieved in light of their educational level, may be assumed to have lost faith in the meritocratic principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to the best of our knowledge, there not evidence of the role of meritocratic beliefs on social reproduction practices. Substantial efforts have been made to explain the early life course mechanisms of social reproductions since Lareau’s (2011) Concerted Cultivation Theory. Middle- and low-class parents differ in their cultural logic of child-rearing. Middle-class parents engage in children’s life experiences in a way that better equip them for adulthood. Organised extra-curricular activities, language use and relation with institutions are at the core of their parenting style. Critically reflecting on this theory, researchers have pointed out this differential is explained by class differences in material resources, and not by cultural logics (Chin and Phillips 2004; Bennett, Lutz, and Jayaram 2012). However, any conclusion related to this debate would be vulnerable without specific measurements of cultural beliefs. &lt;strong&gt;Our research stands out since we include meritocratic belief representing certain aspect of cultural orientation in as the bridge between structural position and child-rearing practice&lt;/strong&gt;. A robust test of meritocratic worldviews as cultural orientations is the main contribution of this study to theory development. The analysis uses data from the China Educational Panel Survey, the first large-scale school-based longitudinal survey conducted in China. To our knowledge, &lt;strong&gt;it is the first quantitative study testing concerted cultivation hypotheses addressing endogeneity issues&lt;/strong&gt;. The empirical strategy combines inverse-probability weighting (IPW) to estimate the causal effect of meritocratic beliefs on concerted cultivation and a two-stage regression model to assess the heterogeneity of this effect across social classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While cultural orientations and their roles in social stratification, educational decisions or parenting styles are widely studied in Western industrialized societies, the role of meritocratic principles in other parts of the world beyond Europe and the US is still under-researched. If meritocratic beliefs legitimize social advantages, they may also affect actions intended to reproduce those advantages as cultural orientations. Weininger, Lareau and Conley (2015) showed that, in the United States, concerted cultivation is not only explained by parents’ objective resources, but also by parents’ cultural orientations. Parenting is a reflection of the parents’ own worldviews and cultural orientations (Bodovski 2010; England and Srivastava 2013). &lt;strong&gt;In this study, we aim to determine whether parents’ meritocratic beliefs affect their parenting style with regard to children’s education and learning.&lt;/strong&gt; We test whether beliefs about hard work and abilities as predictors of scholastic success explain practices of concerted cultivation in China and how they vary across social classes. Accordingly, this study&amp;rsquo;s central innovative potential of this study is the analysis of meritocratic beliefs and child-rearing practices in China -as an Eastern Asian country- that is believed to be characterised by a low level of intergenerational social reproduction (Xie and Zhang 2019; Zhou and Xie 2019). We contribute to the augmentation of Western theories by applying them in a different context. Although there is no equivalent translation into Mandarin Chinese, Confucian philosophy has promoted longstanding meritocratic principles in Western terms. It bonds educational institutions and exam-based qualifications for highly-valued civil service jobs (Hannum et al. 2019). In addition, and in contrast to developed Western societies, educational success in China is not only seen as an individual achievement but is also associated with family honour (Peng 2019). Thus, &lt;strong&gt;China is an ideal case for testing whether parents’ meritocratic narratives play a role in shaping parenting styles in an Eastern Asian society&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there is a trend toward increasing social fluidity throughout the world (Ganzeboom, Treiman, and Ultee 1991; Breen 2010), family socioeconomic status remains a fundamental driver of status attainment. Evidence suggests that societies are not beyond class (Becker and Hadjar 2013), but – depending on societal aspects such as the education system – the meritocratic triad of class of origin, education and class of destination is still a valid concept (Hadjar and Becker 2016). However, the mechanisms through which parents transmit advantage from generation to generation is still a subject for debate (e.g. Roksa and Potter 2011; Carolan 2016). For instance, several studies have discussed whether material or non-material family resources affect children’s educational success (Liu and Xie 2015; Mayer 1997). Family income could be directly invested in more and better education, but non-material resources, such as cognitive skills and culture, also explain how parents’ advantages are transferred to their children. Among these factors, parenting styles have been shown to affect children’s short- and long-term outcomes (Chan and Koo 2011; Pong, Hao, and Gardner 2005; Astone and McLanahan 1991).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coauthor&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chen Chen&lt;/em&gt;, The Chinese University of Hong Kong. Email: ciarachensoc@link.cuhk.edu.hk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andreas Hadjar&lt;/em&gt;, University of Luxembourg. Email: Andreas.Hadjar@uni.lu.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Capital and Students Beliefs about Instructional Quality</title>
      <link>/project/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two main perspectives for understanding teaching effects in the sociological theory. First, the additive perspective understands teaching resources as additives, where instruction is a technological process that leads to achievement. Second, the interactive model proposes that instruction does not produce achievement per se. Instead, opportunities for learning interact with the effects of student characteristics. One of the possible ways in which quality and quantity of instruction could interact with students’ endowments is how they understand opportunities for learning, beliefs that may not be equally distributed across social classes. In this context, &lt;strong&gt;this study aims to understand students’ attributional beliefs about the quality of instruction, and how they interact with the cultural capital of students&lt;/strong&gt;. By using a unique factorial survey, we identified causal attributional beliefs of instruction quality for a representative sample of Chilean primary school students. The findings indicate that students strongly believe that planning time and multidisciplinary team of professional affect teaching quality. Weak beliefs about class size and teachers&amp;rsquo; income satisfaction are found. In addition, the causal attribution of planning time increases with different measurements of students’ cultural capital. Results are discussed considering the contribution of cognitive sociology for studying heterogeneity of teaching effects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ageism under the COVID-19 pandemic and its cross-cultural variations</title>
      <link>/project/aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/aging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by the Interdisciplinary Research Seed Funding of the Faculty of Social Science at The Chinese University of Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Aims&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has made beliefs and attitudes toward older adults a central element of public discourse. In this context, this project is a timely initiative to understand the formation and evolution of aging stereotypes from a cross-cultural perspective. A long body of literature has discussed that agentic and communal
values are crucial factors shaping aging stereotypes. Nevertheless, few studies have simultaneously used large scale cross-national data, and data collected outside of the laboratory, in examining this issue. This project uses novel computational methods, by combining automated text analysis of Twitter messages (study 1) and online factorial experiments (study 2), to examine the public discourse about older adults and &amp;ldquo;open the black box&amp;rdquo; of aging stereotypes. In study 1, we observe the evolution of agentic and communal content in Twitter messages across time and context. In study 2, we use crowdsourcing platforms to conduct online experiments in China and the United States. They seek to identify and untangle the elements contributing to the formation of stereotypes, and how individual-level agentic and communal values influence the consideration of these elements in the stereotype formation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Significance to Interdisciplinary Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project contributes to interdisciplinary research because it combines two research tools from computational social sciences (automated text analysis and an online factorial survey using crowdsourcing platforms) to answer two research questions: 1) How aging stereotypes develop in twitter before and during the COVID-19 pandemic and how these aging beliefs are shaped by cultural contexts (i.e. individualism vs. collectivism) through personal values (agency vs. communion)? 2) What sources contribute to the formation of aging stereotypes and how they are related to cultural values (individualism vs. collectivism) and personal values (agency vs. communion)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Study 1 will use data from Twitter to examine associations between valence of aging stereotypes (warmth vs. competence), cultures (individualism vs. collectivism), and values (agentic vs. communal) based on unsupervised and supervised models. On one hand, with former method, we analyze the text to identify the latent structure of textual corpora, which is a method increasingly used in cultural sociology. On the other hand, the study of emotions and values in psychology have mainly relied on supervised models based on machine learning. We combine both traditions for a more comprehensive understanding of the text. Moreover, study 1 has an interdisciplinary theoretical contribution to examine the complexity of aging views, considering its sociological and psychological underpinnings. From a theoretical perspective, the discourses contained in the texts are aggregated to understand beliefs about older adults in what cultural sociologists have framed as public culture. By tracking public discourse, we examine how a moral shock (COVID-19 pandemic) could have affected shared beliefs about a vulnerable population. Thus, we directly speak to the literature that considers cultural change as a mainly local phenomenon and driven by cohort replacement. Our study will contribute to a more nuanced and balanced view of possibilities for cultural change. In addition, public disclosures of beliefs towards older adults during the pandemic can be explained from the perspective of psychology. Specifically, individuals&amp;rsquo; beliefs toward outgroups can be assessed in terms of the warmth and competence aspects according to the stereotype content model (Fiske et al., 2002). Since older age groups are regarded as high in warmth but low in competence than younger age groups (Cuddy &amp;amp; Fiske, 2002), we can identify changes of ageism on Twitter across time and contexts. Moreover, we will assess how cultural values (individualism vs. collectivism) and personal values (agency vs. communion) impact contents of aging stereotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Study 2 relies on psychological and sociological rationales to &amp;ldquo;open the black box&amp;rdquo; of aging stereotypes. We will further examine how different domains of life in old age lead to subjective social status, a common variable used in stratification beliefs, which is entailed by stereotypes. In study 2, targeting on participants from two cultures
(individualism in the United States and collectivism in China), we will use an online factorial survey to experimentally manipulate cultural, social, economic, and physical elements and estimate their contributions to aging stereotypes formation, and how this process varies across individuals when considering agentic/communal values. With this study, the association between individual values and aging stereotype is examined through the lens of social psychology; moreover, cultural sociology provides insights to understand how beliefs about certain groups are formed and shaped by cultural values as rule-alike-structures. Using a factorial survey approach, we aim to provide further evidence in understanding how different elements suggested by study 1 are combined to
explain stereotypes toward older people. In addition, we also move forward the literatures by incorporating the agentic and communal individual values into the understanding of how older age groups are represented in the social media discourse in times of COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborators&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chunyan May&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Psychology, The Chinese University of Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Xuqian Chen&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Psychology, The Chinese University of Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chen Dan&lt;/em&gt;, Department of Sociology, The Chinese University of Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Myth of Hard Work</title>
      <link>/project/meritocracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/meritocracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In modern societies, meritocracy is a principle which provides the basis for reward allocation based on achievement rather than ascription (Mijs 2016b; Tsay et al. 2003; Young 1958). Defenders of meritocratic ideals (Herrnstein and Murray 1996; Saunders 1995) indicate that it serves to two purposes: first, enables to allocate efficiently scarce resources and, second, incentivizes effort. However, unequal and underserved starting positions lead to the understanding that meritocracy violates its own merit principle. It legitimates societal inequalities as justly deserved, and misfortune becomes a personal failure (Mijs 2016b). However, the cross-national and comparative efforts of legitimization researcher have not come along with longitudinal evidence to rule out bidirectional effects (Mijs 2016a, 2019). Either way, those competing perspective could apply to different experiences of social mobility, professional career, educational achievement or any sort of success. In this context, &lt;strong&gt;this study is aimed to test these two perspectives simultaneously in the case of the Chinese educational system: How do parents’ meritocratic beliefs and children’s educational performance are affected by each other?&lt;/strong&gt; We focus on the educational system because it is the most important mechanism of stratification in post-industrial societies (Bell 1999). By understanding the role of parental meritocratic beliefs in the educational system we closely examine how meritocratic beliefs shape and are shaped by success in society. Although China could not be classified as a post-industrial country, since 2012 the share of the tertiary sector overtook the secondary sector as the most important economic sector (National Bureau of Statistics 2012). Therefore, meritocratic beliefs are examined in a juncture of industrial transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This question arises classical discussions in sociology of culture regarding the relationship between culture and action&lt;/strong&gt; (Frye 2012; Schwarz 2018; Vaisey 2009). However, as Vaisey and Valentino (2018) diagnose, beliefs are usually sidelined by cultural sociologists. Indeed, meritocratic beliefs could be understood as narratives if we applied the operationalization of culture provided by Small, Harding and Lamont (2010). Narratives are “causally linked sequence of events in people’s minds”  (Small et al. 2010:16) and the classical definition of meritocracy is where success is predicted by non-ascriptive characteristics such as effort, intelligence, and non-cognitive skills. Therefore, parental beliefs about meritocracy are narratives of how rewards are allocated in society. Hence, by discussing the reciprocal effects of parental beliefs and educational outcomes we engage in a broader discussion about culture and action literature.
This article makes several contributions to the literature. First, &lt;strong&gt;we test simultaneously two competing hypotheses about the role of meritocratic beliefs in the educational system&lt;/strong&gt;. It is enabled by a theoretical rationale and rich longitudinal data. Understanding meritocratic beliefs as narratives, a dual-process model of culture (Vaisey 2009; Vaisey and Lizardo 2010) is applied to derive reciprocal effects hypotheses. Moreover, the two waves of the China Educational Panel Survey allows using autoregressive cross-lagged structural models for disentangling the theorized reciprocal effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;strong&gt;the Chinese case is a unique setting for studying meritocratic beliefs&lt;/strong&gt;. Paradoxically, there is no equivalent word to meritocracy in Chinese. It is often translated as elitism (英才教育), which ignore its antecedents. However, Chinese culture has longstanding meritocratic principles in western terms, grounded on the Confucian philosophy. It bonds educational institutions and examination to qualifications for highly-valued civil service jobs (Hannum et al. 2019). Folk tales of hard work, such as Kuang Heng’s story, illustrates how meritocratic beliefs have permeated Chinese society. He was a poor kid who lived during the Han dynasty. His family could not afford candles for studying at night. Because of his commitment to become a civil servant, he used light coming from his neighbors’ houses. Thus, through hard work, he reached the position of emperor’s hand. In addition, a recent study has shown (Mijs 2019) that countries with higher inequality tend to explain success in meritocratic terms. In the case of China, rapid economic development and social inequality bring the justificatory role of meritocratic narratives, alongside his hypothesized motivational effect, into sharper relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;this study specifies differences between attributional beliefs regarding skills and hard work&lt;/strong&gt;. Critics of the role of meritocracy argue that meritocratic beliefs contradict themselves. People have different starting points, and through meritocratic principles, they are signified as deserved (Mijs 2016b). A large body of evidence using twins’ studies has shown that family and genetic endowments affect cognitive and non-cognitive skills (Daw, Guo, and Harris 2015; Felson 2014; Nielsen 2006; Pokropek and Sikora 2015; Teachman 1997). Taken together, this literature suggests that family nurtures the development of skills. Nevertheless, nobody chooses the family where one is born into. Indeed, most of these studies are built upon the strong assumption that there is no assortative mating, which ultimately may affect genetic endowments. Henceforth, we could critically examine meritocratic beliefs independently. Thus, this study seeks to explore the consistency of both components of meritocracy -skills and hard work- and their potential heterogeneous relationships with academic performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
