<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Francisco Olivos</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Francisco Olivos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Capital and Students Beliefs about Instructional Quality</title>
      <link>/project/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two main perspectives for understanding teaching effects in the sociological theory. First, the additive perspective understands teaching resources as additives, where instruction is a technological process that leads to achievement. Second, the interactive model proposes that instruction does not produce achievement per se. Instead, opportunities for learning interact with the effects of student characteristics. One of the possible ways in which quality and quantity of instruction could interact with students’ endowments is how they understand opportunities for learning, beliefs that may not be equally distributed across social classes. In this context, &lt;strong&gt;this study aims to understand students’ attributional beliefs about the quality of instruction, and how they interact with the cultural capital of students&lt;/strong&gt;. By using a unique factorial survey, we identified causal attributional beliefs of instruction quality for a representative sample of Chilean primary school students. The findings indicate that students strongly believe that planning time and multidisciplinary team of professional affect teaching quality. Weak beliefs about class size and teachers&amp;rsquo; income satisfaction are found. In addition, the causal attribution of planning time increases with different measurements of students’ cultural capital. Results are discussed considering the contribution of cognitive sociology for studying heterogeneity of teaching effects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Children Beliefs and Judgements with Factorial Surveys</title>
      <link>/project/children/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last decades, &lt;strong&gt;social sciences have witnessed a rapid growth of the use of factorial surveys to study beliefs and social judgments&lt;/strong&gt; (Wallander 2009). They have been applied in different fields and different efforts have been made in its validation (Dülmer 2007; Lang 2018; Liebe et al. 2017; Sauer et al. 2011, 2014). Among those efforts, the discussion of its feasibility in general populations enabled to include them in large scale surveys and answer generalizable questions (Sauer et al. 2011). Besides the interest in developed countries, nowadays their use and validation have been also spread to less developed contexts (Castillo, Olivos, and Azar 2018; Liebe et al. 2017; Mateo Piñones and Valenzuela Carvallo 2017). However, &lt;strong&gt;few studies have advanced on the validation of factorial survey on specific populations&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. Teti et al. 2016), which could challenge this popular method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our research question is motivated by the substantial contribution that factorial surveys could to make children research&lt;/strong&gt;. To our knowledge, there are not applications to this subpopulation. Factorial surveys are an experimental tool which allows addressing the endogeneity of beliefs and judgments (Hainmueller, Hopkins, and Yamamoto 2014; Olivos, 2019). Beliefs are organized in an interconnected system. Therefore, the dependency of beliefs difficulties the isolation of causal effects of particular units of the system. By using a factorial survey, we could identify the causal effects of children’s beliefs on their evaluations, judgments or decision-making. Understanding children’s perceptions, beliefs, and opinions provides relevant information about the determinants of their behaviors and decision-making process. It is consistent with the widely accepted idea that children should no longer only be seen, but also heard in child research (Scott 2008). Rational choice theorists suggest that people, including children and adolescents, act in light of beliefs (Breen 1999; Morgan 2005). In late childhood, and depending on the society, children may take different decisions such as sexual initiation, substance use or educational track choice, among others. These decisions are guided by beliefs, dispositions, and preferences. Hence, factorial surveys are a powerful analytic approach to understand the complexity of children beliefs and their decision-making process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a factorial survey module, respondents may rate a sample of fictitious descriptions of persons, situations or institutions called vignettes. The larger the number of vignettes, the higher the cognitive demand of working on this exercise (Auspurg and Hintz 2014; Sauer et al. 2011). It could directly hinder the consistency of responses when evaluating the vignettes. &lt;strong&gt;Thus, in this study, we aim to discuss the feasibility of factorial surveys on children populations by means of examining the consistency of their responses&lt;/strong&gt;. Children are seldom included as part of survey samples, mainly because of concerns about the cognitive abilities “to process and respond to structured questions about behavior, perceptions, opinions, and beliefs” (Scott 2008:88). Therefore, this study is an important contribution to the field of survey methodology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the experimental design, &lt;strong&gt;factorial surveys are an indirect questioning method, suitable for measuring sensitive issues&lt;/strong&gt; (Auspurg et al. 2015). Instead of asking what people think about a certain dimension, they evaluate it in a fictitious scenario. According to Lusk and Nordwood (2010), the assumption underlying indirect questioning is that when answering direct questions people want to make themselves look good, but they are not concerned with making others look good. For instance, answering the direct question “Are single-parent families happy?” could be affected by the avoidance of socially desirable answers. However, in FSs, we could include “family structure” as a dimension describing a fictitious family and ask about the level of happiness of that family. Studies using factorial survey have been applied to investigate professional judgments about children abuse reducing successfully social desirability (O’Toole et al. 1994, 1999). In the case of research with children, it is particularly challenging because children may report more socially desirable behaviors than other groups (Camerini and Schulz 2018; Havermans, Vanassche, and Matthijs 2015).  By avoiding social desirability, factorial surveys open the black box of children’s thoughts, preferences and dispositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study uses data from the 2016 Study About Quality of Education from the Perspective of the Key Actors of the System. It comprises a large and representative sample of Chilean students from 5th to 8th grades. The questionnaire sought to understand students’ judgments about instruction quality. In addition to the factorial survey module, we use student’s characteristics and perceived difficulty to identify potential predictors of consistency. The context of the study offers upper-bound conditions for our validation. Chilean students are outperformed by almost all the students of OCDE countries in reading standardized tests. Therefore, &lt;strong&gt;our estimations could be considered as a conservative test. Any study using factorial survey on children populations from more developed countries could consider our findings as a “worse-case scenario”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surveyed students are on average 11.9 years old with a standard deviation of 1.4. As Borgers, de Leeuw and Hox (2000) explain, children at that age could be considered in the development of formal though stage. Cognitive functions such as formal thinking, logic, and negations are well developed, which suggests that they could answer this kind of instruments. Most children in this age can articulate their beliefs and opinions and, with some adaptations, surveys designed for adults could be used with them (Scott 2008). However, children in this stage are highly sensitive to the context. They could easily be distracted during the surveys or being affected by their classmates. Motivation and boredom could also hamper the quality of the data (Borgers et al. 2000; Scott 2008). &lt;strong&gt;Consequently, even though they could possess the enough cognitive abilities, we may evaluate the feasibility of using factorial surveys with children samples.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coauthor&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Minhui Liu&lt;/em&gt;, Pan Sutong Shanghai-Hong Kong Economic Policy Research Institute, Lignan University. Email: minhuiliu@ln.edu.hk&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Myth of Hard Work</title>
      <link>/project/meritocracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/meritocracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In modern societies, meritocracy is a principle which provides the basis for reward allocation based on achievement rather than ascription (Mijs 2016b; Tsay et al. 2003; Young 1958). Defenders of meritocratic ideals (Herrnstein and Murray 1996; Saunders 1995) indicate that it serves to two purposes: first, enables to allocate efficiently scarce resources and, second, incentivizes effort. However, unequal and underserved starting positions lead to the understanding that meritocracy violates its own merit principle. It legitimates societal inequalities as justly deserved, and misfortune becomes a personal failure (Mijs 2016b). However, the cross-national and comparative efforts of legitimization researcher have not come along with longitudinal evidence to rule out bidirectional effects (Mijs 2016a, 2019). Either way, those competing perspective could apply to different experiences of social mobility, professional career, educational achievement or any sort of success. In this context, &lt;strong&gt;this study is aimed to test these two perspectives simultaneously in the case of the Chinese educational system: How do parents’ meritocratic beliefs and children’s educational performance are affected by each other?&lt;/strong&gt; We focus on the educational system because it is the most important mechanism of stratification in post-industrial societies (Bell 1999). By understanding the role of parental meritocratic beliefs in the educational system we closely examine how meritocratic beliefs shape and are shaped by success in society. Although China could not be classified as a post-industrial country, since 2012 the share of the tertiary sector overtook the secondary sector as the most important economic sector (National Bureau of Statistics 2012). Therefore, meritocratic beliefs are examined in a juncture of industrial transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This question arises classical discussions in sociology of culture regarding the relationship between culture and action&lt;/strong&gt; (Frye 2012; Schwarz 2018; Vaisey 2009). However, as Vaisey and Valentino (2018) diagnose, beliefs are usually sidelined by cultural sociologists. Indeed, meritocratic beliefs could be understood as narratives if we applied the operationalization of culture provided by Small, Harding and Lamont (2010). Narratives are “causally linked sequence of events in people’s minds”  (Small et al. 2010:16) and the classical definition of meritocracy is where success is predicted by non-ascriptive characteristics such as effort, intelligence, and non-cognitive skills. Therefore, parental beliefs about meritocracy are narratives of how rewards are allocated in society. Hence, by discussing the reciprocal effects of parental beliefs and educational outcomes we engage in a broader discussion about culture and action literature.
This article makes several contributions to the literature. First, &lt;strong&gt;we test simultaneously two competing hypotheses about the role of meritocratic beliefs in the educational system&lt;/strong&gt;. It is enabled by a theoretical rationale and rich longitudinal data. Understanding meritocratic beliefs as narratives, a dual-process model of culture (Vaisey 2009; Vaisey and Lizardo 2010) is applied to derive reciprocal effects hypotheses. Moreover, the two waves of the China Educational Panel Survey allows using autoregressive cross-lagged structural models for disentangling the theorized reciprocal effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;strong&gt;the Chinese case is a unique setting for studying meritocratic beliefs&lt;/strong&gt;. Paradoxically, there is no equivalent word to meritocracy in Chinese. It is often translated as elitism (英才教育), which ignore its antecedents. However, Chinese culture has longstanding meritocratic principles in western terms, grounded on the Confucian philosophy. It bonds educational institutions and examination to qualifications for highly-valued civil service jobs (Hannum et al. 2019). Folk tales of hard work, such as Kuang Heng’s story, illustrates how meritocratic beliefs have permeated Chinese society. He was a poor kid who lived during the Han dynasty. His family could not afford candles for studying at night. Because of his commitment to become a civil servant, he used light coming from his neighbors’ houses. Thus, through hard work, he reached the position of emperor’s hand. In addition, a recent study has shown (Mijs 2019) that countries with higher inequality tend to explain success in meritocratic terms. In the case of China, rapid economic development and social inequality bring the justificatory role of meritocratic narratives, alongside his hypothesized motivational effect, into sharper relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;this study specifies differences between attributional beliefs regarding skills and hard work&lt;/strong&gt;. Critics of the role of meritocracy argue that meritocratic beliefs contradict themselves. People have different starting points, and through meritocratic principles, they are signified as deserved (Mijs 2016b). A large body of evidence using twins’ studies has shown that family and genetic endowments affect cognitive and non-cognitive skills (Daw, Guo, and Harris 2015; Felson 2014; Nielsen 2006; Pokropek and Sikora 2015; Teachman 1997). Taken together, this literature suggests that family nurtures the development of skills. Nevertheless, nobody chooses the family where one is born into. Indeed, most of these studies are built upon the strong assumption that there is no assortative mating, which ultimately may affect genetic endowments. Henceforth, we could critically examine meritocratic beliefs independently. Thus, this study seeks to explore the consistency of both components of meritocracy -skills and hard work- and their potential heterogeneous relationships with academic performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
